<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Homepage on Marian&#39;s Garden</title>
    <link>https://www.sendung.de/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Homepage on Marian&#39;s Garden</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>de-de</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 12:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.sendung.de/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Warum ich WhatsApp nicht nutze</title>
      <link>https://www.sendung.de/2025-07-03/warum-kein-whatsapp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sendung.de/2025-07-03/warum-kein-whatsapp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Immer wieder mal komme ich in die Situation, dass ich zu einer WhatsApp-Gruppe eingeladen werde. Und dann muss ich leider ablehnen und erklären, dass ich WhatsApp nicht benutze. Selten habe ich dann die Zeit, die gründe ausführlich zu erklären. Deshalb schreibe ich sie hier auf.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Eine Sache vorweg: es ist mühselig.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ich werde damit gerne als der Querulant hingestellt, der eine eigentlich einfache Angelegenheit kompliziert macht. &amp;ldquo;Alle benutzen doch WhatsApp&amp;rdquo;, also wäre es ja das einfachste, ich würde mich ihnen anschließen. Aber ich sehe das etwas anders. Ich bin nicht das Problem, sondern derjenige, der auf das Problem aufmerksam macht. Und es gibt ja durchaus Alternativen.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relative humidity is misleading</title>
      <link>https://www.sendung.de/2024-09-23/relative-humidity-dewpoint/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 21:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sendung.de/2024-09-23/relative-humidity-dewpoint/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As many people, we have a basement where we store way too many things. On top of that, it&amp;rsquo;s where we wash and tumble-dry our clothes. Our biggest concern is that we might get mold one day. High air humidity is a big factor in mold growth, so we aim to keep the humidity low and we constantly monitor the humidity.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-keep-the-basement-dry&#34;&gt;How to keep the basement dry?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the beginning we started with putting little hygrometers in the basement rooms. These were soon rising above 60, 65, sometimes over 70 percent. So let&amp;rsquo;s open the windows and let the humid air out.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy efficiency of programming languages</title>
      <link>https://www.sendung.de/2022-07-24/programming-languages-energy-efficiency/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2022 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sendung.de/2022-07-24/programming-languages-energy-efficiency/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Servers are taking an &lt;a href=&#34;https://digital-strategy.ec.europa.eu/en/library/energy-efficient-cloud-computing-technologies-and-policies-eco-friendly-cloud-market&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; &gt;ever growing share&lt;/a&gt; of our electricity usage. Of course, they exist to run applications. And the energy consumption is, to a large degree, determined by the applications running on them.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ironically, servers turn electricical energy into thermal energy and thus contribute to global warming in a very concrete sense.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When I look around, I don&amp;rsquo;t see a lot of discussion happening around the &lt;strong&gt;responsibility of application developers&lt;/strong&gt; regarding energy usage and the impact this has on climate change. We are used to juggling often contradicting goals like software maintainability, development and release cycles, user experience, and security. Yet we fail to take into account how our applications could be made more friendly to our climate. And, to be honest, that makes me quite unhappy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Website tech update</title>
      <link>https://www.sendung.de/2022-07-22/website-tech-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sendung.de/2022-07-22/website-tech-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It was time for several updates. This site is now&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;hosted by &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.codeberg.org/codeberg-pages/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; &gt;Codeberg&lt;/a&gt; instead of GitHub,&lt;/del&gt; Edit: doesn&amp;rsquo;t work yet, so for now it&amp;rsquo;s still GitHub.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;created using &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; &gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; instead of Jekyll,&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;using a different &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/apvarun/digital-garden-hugo-theme&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; &gt;template/theme&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m also &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/apvarun/digital-garden-hugo-theme/pulls?q=is%3Apr&amp;#43;author%3Amarians&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; &gt;contributing&lt;/a&gt; a few additions to the Hugo theme.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mit dem Mountainbike auf den Grünten? Nein.</title>
      <link>https://www.sendung.de/2020-09-04/mit-dem-mtb-auf-den-gruenten/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Sep 2020 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sendung.de/2020-09-04/mit-dem-mtb-auf-den-gruenten/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Wer ins Oberallgäu fährt und eine Leidenschaft für das Radfahren mitbringt, wird vielleicht auf die Idee kommen, mit dem Mountainbike auf den Grünten, den &amp;ldquo;Wächter des Allgäus&amp;rdquo;, zu fahren.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spoiler: es macht keinen Sinn und ist gefährlich.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Mir ging es auch so. Der Grünten ist ein alleinstehender, attraktiver Gipfel und mit 1738 m höher als viele andere Berge in der Umgebung. Außerdem gibt es (außer für Mitarbeiter_innen des Bayerischen Rundfunk) keine Bergbahn. Also bleibt einem nur, aus eigener Kraft hinauf zu kommen. Wäre es möglich, das mit dem Mountainbike zu machen?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gekommen, um zu bleiben: Gründe, jetzt das Fediverse zu betreten</title>
      <link>https://www.sendung.de/2019-01-06/gruende-jetzt-das-fediverse-zu-betreten/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jan 2019 21:18:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sendung.de/2019-01-06/gruende-jetzt-das-fediverse-zu-betreten/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Zuletzt aktualisiert am 16. Oktober 2022&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In meinem vorigen Beitrag &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sendung.de/2018-12-22/wir-treffen-uns-im-fediverse/&#34; &gt;Wir treffen uns im Fediverse&lt;/a&gt; habe ich über dezentrale soziale Netzwerke und das Fediverse geschrieben.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Verglichen mit den großen, zentralisierten Vorbildern ist das Fediverse im Moment klein. &lt;a href=&#34;https://the-federation.info/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; &gt;the-federation.info&lt;/a&gt; listet etwas über 6,1 Millionen Accounts. Etwa 580.000 davon waren innerhalb der letzten 30 Tage aktiv. Lohnt es sich da, Zeit zu investieren, sich ein Netzwerk aufzubauen und Tools zu testen? Oder sogar darüber zu reden und andere Menschen, die wir im Fediverse vermissen würden, zum Mitmachen zu überreden?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wir treffen uns im Fediverse!</title>
      <link>https://www.sendung.de/2018-12-22/wir-treffen-uns-im-fediverse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Dec 2018 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sendung.de/2018-12-22/wir-treffen-uns-im-fediverse/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Der Jahreswechsel steht an, und damit drei Gründe, sich mit Alternativen für die zentralen sozialen Netzwerke zu befassen:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Wir brauchen natürlich einen guten Vorsatz für das neue Jahr (oder eher für die ersten paar Wochen des neuen Jahrs)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Wir haben vielleicht ein bisschen Urlaub und Zeit&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Die Bekanntwerdung des &lt;a href=&#34;https://netzpolitik.org/2018/die-ultimative-liste-so-viele-datenskandale-gab-es-2018-bei-facebook/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; &gt;neusten Facebook-Skandals&lt;/a&gt; liegt erst wenige Tage zurück&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Die Facebooks und Twitters können nicht unsere Zukunft sein.&lt;/strong&gt; Brauchst Du Gründe? Die Macht, die diese Konzerne konzentrieren, ist gefährlich. Sie gehen bestenfalls schlampig mit unseren Daten um und entziehen sich nahezu jeder Kontrolle. Sie beeinflussen durch intransparente Algorithmen, womit wir uns beschäftigen. Sie werden zum SPOF (Single Point of Failure) für unsere Demokratie.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ESP8266 publishing DHT temperature and humidity via Web Thing API</title>
      <link>https://www.sendung.de/2018-11-07/esp8266-dht-webthing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Nov 2018 09:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sendung.de/2018-11-07/esp8266-dht-webthing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After reading through some of the Mozilla IoT examples, I got an ESP8266 to publish temperature and humidity values via the Web Thing API.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here is the code:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;script src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/marians/15440a219a72f95b31421e646dffc11f.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gist.github.com/marians/15440a219a72f95b31421e646dffc11f&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; &gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zusammen braucht man weniger</title>
      <link>https://www.sendung.de/2018-10-21/zusammen-nachhaltiger/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Oct 2018 17:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sendung.de/2018-10-21/zusammen-nachhaltiger/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vom (Gedanken-)Experiment des Müllvermeidens zu einer hyperlokalen Tauschplattform für den täglichen Bedarf&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Language notice: this is a post about how to share resources between neighbours. As I am living in Germany and my neighbours speak German mostly, I feel like I have to write this in German.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Eigentlich möchte ich gar nicht erst anfangen, zu erklären, warum. Eigentlich möchte ich einfach voraussetzen, dass wir alle der Meinung sind, dass wir unseren Fußabdruck so klein halten sollten, wie möglich. Dass wir nachhaltig leben sollten. Deutlich nachhaltiger, als wir es im Moment tun.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Re-claiming my content</title>
      <link>https://www.sendung.de/2018-10-16/reclaiming-my-content/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2018 21:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sendung.de/2018-10-16/reclaiming-my-content/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I was stuck in a commute situation, so I had a rare moment of boredom and reflection and decided to google &lt;code&gt;jekyll microblogging&lt;/code&gt; to find out how easy it would be to make my blog fit smaller content chunks. I felt like gathering what I&amp;rsquo;m emitting on my home turf, at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sendung.de/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; &gt;www.sendung.de&lt;/a&gt;, which is a Jekyll site served by Github Pages.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What I found was &lt;a href=&#34;http://fionavoss.blog/2018/04/01/microblogging-in-jekyll/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; &gt;a great post by Fiona Voss&lt;/a&gt; that shows a way to re-claim my content by using my own blog as the center of my conversation in other channels. And it opens a door to phenomenons like the &lt;a href=&#34;https://indieweb.org/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; &gt;IndieWeb&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://indieweb.org/Micropub&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; &gt;MicroPub&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://indieweb.org/POSSE&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; &gt;POSSE&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing the Tour de France General Classification Build-Up</title>
      <link>https://www.sendung.de/2017-07-16/visualizing-tour-de-france-general-classification-buildup/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2017 23:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sendung.de/2017-07-16/visualizing-tour-de-france-general-classification-buildup/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The 104th edition of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.letour.fr/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; &gt;Tour de France&lt;/a&gt; is in full swing. Time to have a look at how the General Classification developed so far.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Wait, what? General Who? Tour de WTF?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;OK, sorry. If you have no interest in the sport of riding bicycles and never heard of the most popular bike race in the world, maybe start with a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tour_de_France&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; &gt;Wikipedia article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To the rest who knows at least that there is such a thing as the Tour de France, let&amp;rsquo;s revisit how that race works. The Tour (as friends call it) is a stage race. The nearly 200 riders, belonging to teams of nine riders each, ride twenty-one stages overall, over the course of twenty-three days.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Idea: DIY Sourdough Incubator</title>
      <link>https://www.sendung.de/2016-12-13/diy-sourdough-incubator/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 21:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sendung.de/2016-12-13/diy-sourdough-incubator/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The idea of &lt;del&gt;breaking bad&lt;/del&gt; baking bread, really good bread, is super-fascinating to me. I got recently amazed by this guy named Lutz Geißler, who seems to be on a mission and already published nearly 800 bread recipes in his blog called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ploetzblog.de/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; &gt;Plötzblog&lt;/a&gt;. I found him via an episode of the radio show &lt;a href=&#34;http://www1.wdr.de/mediathek/audio/wdr5/wdr5-alles-in-butter/index.html&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; &gt;Alles in Butter&lt;/a&gt; on local radio WDR5. If you want to find out more about him, bread and his driving forces, check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://cre.fm/cre213-brot&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; &gt;this lengthy and fascinating talk&lt;/a&gt; with him and Tim Pritlove (all in German).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About me</title>
      <link>https://www.sendung.de/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sendung.de/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hello 👋 &amp;ndash; I am Marian&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Born 1977, living in Rösrath near Cologne, Nordrhein-Westfalen, Germany. Son, brother, father, partner. Designer (taught)/engineer (self-taught) with a focus on user experience.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If you care about pronouns, mine are: &lt;strong&gt;he / him / his&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Becoming a &lt;strong&gt;parent&lt;/strong&gt;, they say, changes everything. And it&amp;rsquo;s true. Since my daughter was born in 2016, I feel like almost everything I do, I do for her to some degree. And it got me a lot more worried about the direction we are heading with our planet. I can&amp;rsquo;t help but think what unlikely coincidence it was that on this tiny planet it was possible that life as we know it could evolve. We are obliged to do everything we can to sustain the results of this coincidence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>🔗 Links</title>
      <link>https://www.sendung.de/links/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.sendung.de/links/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some links to sites, people, things I recommend.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; &gt;Low←Tech Magazine&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; interesting ideas, deep research&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://politbanause.jimdofree.com/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; &gt;Politbanause&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; watches German politics madness&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://marcusnoble.co.uk/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; &gt;Marcus Noble&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; A dear colleague at Giant Swarm&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://graslutscher.de/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; &gt;Der Graslutscher&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; German green tech journalist&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cleanteching.beehiiv.com/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; &gt;CleanTech Ing.&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; Tech solutions for the climate crisis (German)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
